# PHIL HENRICKSON

phil.henrickson@gmail.com · Madison, WI · Personal Site · GitHub · LinkedIn

#### **SUMMARY**

Data Scientist with scientific research background, strong communication skills, and years of industry experience in a client-facing role. Demonstrated experience in scoping, developing, and delivering data/analytics projects, with an emphasis on predictive modeling, causal inference, and data visualization. Accomplished public speaker with featured talks and presentations at conferences and meetups throughout the state of Wisconsin.

#### **SKILLS**

## Languages and Tools

Proficient: R, Python, Git/GitHub, SQL, Quarto, Shiny, Markdown, Tableau, Alteryx

Intermediate: Docker, GCP/AWS/Azure

 $\textbf{Selected Coursework}: \ \textbf{Applied Machine Learning, Causal Inference, Statistical Learning, Maximum Likelihood Estimation, Time \textbf{Maximum Likelihood Estimation} \\$ 

Series, Research Design, Survey Design

#### **EDUCATION**

## Florida State University

Tallahassee, FL

Doctor of Philosophy: Political Science

Dissertation: Applied Predictive Modeling for Measurement and Inference

in International Conflict and Political Violence

Texas A&M University

College Station, TX

Bachelor of Science: Political Science

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### **AE Business Solutions**

2019-Present

Senior Data Scientist

Madison, WI

- Work in a client-facing, project delivery role for data science and analytics use cases across a variety of industries in the public and private sector
- Serve as technical liaison between data science teams and senior leadership, translating complex analyses into actionable recommendations to inform strategic decisions
- Building data pipelines and deploying predictive models within DevOps frameworks
- · Assess organizational practices for data science and audit models for performance, fairness, and bias
- Deliver hands-on training and "office hours" advising for clients on topics within the fields of data science

#### **AE Business Solutions**

2018-2019

Business Intelligence Engineer

Madison, WI

- Developing interactive dashboards and data visualizations to communicate insights and statistical methods to general public
- Training business and data analysts in research methods, data preparation, and data visualization (R, Alteryx, Tableau)

## Florida State University

2013-2018

Research Assistant

Tallahassee, FL

- Performed statistical modeling in R and Stata for prediction and hypothesis testing in social science research.
- Assisted professors by collecting, cleaning, and preparing data sets for data visualization and presentation in academic research papers.
- Literature reviews of sub fields in international relations, comparative politics, statistics, and computer science.

#### Instructor

- Created original syllabi and lecture materials for Political Violence, Civil Wars, and International Relations classes.
- Assigned semester-long research papers, working with students to develop their academic writing skills and mentor their applications for graduate school.
- Taught programming with R to graduate students and held supplementary sessions for statistical modeling and programming.

#### PERSONAL PROJECTS

Most of my work with clients is under NDA, making it difficult to provide detailed examples of my work. I do, however, frequently work on side projects in my free time to explore new methods and techniques that I can use in my consultant work. Here are some examples:

- Created package for collecting BoardGameGeek (BGG) data to train predictive models at the BGG community level (complexity, average rating, etc) for upcoming board game releases
- Trained predictive models for individual users to recommend new games to individuals based on their collections.
- Developed pipelines to collect data on upcoming releases and deliver predictions from a suite of models (penalized linear regressions, xgboost, lightgbm) via GitHub Actions, Google Cloud Storage, and Quarto

### College Football Predictions and Rankings

2024

- Estimating opponent-adjusted team offensive/defensive efficiency for all FBS teams at the weekly level using play by play data and predicted points added per play.
- Use team efficiency ratings as inputs into my (Bayesian) game prediction model to estimate team ratings and simulate upcoming college football games.